Vaughn Shoemaker Cartoons
Vaughn Shoemaker Cartoons
1956-1967
Shoemaker, Vaughn, 1902-
1.5 linear ft.
30 original editorial cartoons by the Pulitzer Prize-winning American cartoonist.
2644642
Biographical History
Vaughn Shoemaker (1902-1991) was an American cartoonist. Shoemaker served as editorial cartoonist for the Chicago Daily News from 1922-1952, where he created his famous character, John Q. Public. Also during his tenure with the Daily News, he was awarded the Pulitzer Prize twice—once in 1938 for his cartoon "The Road Back", and again in 1947 for his cartoon "Still Racing His Shadow". Later in his career, Shoemaker worked for the New York Herald Tribune, the Chicago American and Chicago Today. Vaughn Shoemaker retired in 1972.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Vaughn Shoemaker Cartoons collection contains 30 editorial cartoons published between the years 1956-1967. The cartoons cover a range of Cold War themes including the nuclear arms race, world communism, relations with the Soviet Union and Castro's Cuba. Shoemaker's signature John Q. Public character appears in several of the cartoons.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in alphabetical order by title.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Shoemaker, Vaughn, 1902-; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1961-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vaughn Shoemaker, 1969.
Inventory
- Editorial Cartoons, 30 items; (crayon, pen and ink on paper, approx. 13 ½ x 17 in.)
  - All in Favor Say, 'I'!, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Annual Lip Service, 1961 Oct 18 (Box 1)
  - Chef's Special - Russian Bear Steak, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Election Year Chivalry, 1960 April 12 (Box 1)
  - Good News for Vietnam, No Steel Strike!, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Halftime, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Hee, Hee, How You Doin' Comrades?, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Highway Courtesy on the Road to Freedom, 1959 (Box 1)
  - In This War, We Shoot First, 1961 Sept 18 (Box 1)
  - Just Who's Side are We On, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Keeping Our Powder Dry, 1966 Aug 18 (Box 1)
  - Khrushchev's Chickens, 1961 June 15 (Box 1)
  - Let's Start Being Careful What We Sow, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Life of a Census Taker Wasn't Always So Complicated, 1960 Mar 29 (Box 1)
  - New Jet Age, 1962 May 28 (Box 1)
  - Notice Any Family Resemblance?, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Praise Allah and Pass the Ammunition, 1958 (Box 1)
  - 68 Fashions?, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Still Behind the Eight Ball, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Temporarily Safe?, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Those Golden Eggs, 1961 Jul 12 (Box 1)
  - Those Macmillan-Kennedy Talks, 1962 April 25 (Box 1)
  - Trick or Treat, 1961 Oct 18 (Box 1)
  - The Trouble With Kittens - They Grow Up, 1967 Jul 14 (Box 1)
  - Turning Up the Gas?, 1958 Jul 15 (Box 1)
  - Uncle Gets Blamed for Everything, 1958 (Box 1)
  - We Forget We were Kids Once, 1963 Oct 21 (Box 1)
  - Will the Real Communist Please Stand Up, 1963 June 26 (Box 1)
  - Won't Stay Buried, 1959 Oct 26 (Box 1)
  - Yes, Past Time to Have It Out, 1961 April 5 (Box 1)